Finding Aid for Ann Arbor Anti-Substance Abuse Task Force records, 1987-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ann Arbor Anti-Substance Abuse Task Force records 1987-1992
Ann Arbor Anti-Substance Abuse Task Force.
1.5 linear feet.
0639 Bj 2
Task Force established by the Ann Arbor City Council on May 16, 1988 in response to a perceived growth in drug use and abuse in Ann Arbor. Letters and memoranda of Terry Martin, Task Force Chair, agendas and meetings of minutes, collected data and final report to council, and other assorted clippings and documents.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was created by Terry Martin, Task Force Chair, then given to Bradley Spencer, co-founder of the Community Action on Substance Abuse (donor no. 8076 ), who in 2005 donated the files to the Bentley Historical Library. Additional records were received in 2007.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Anti-Substance Abuse Task Force was established by the Ann Arbor City Council on May 16, 1988 in a resolution submitted by Republican councilmember Terry Martin. The task force was established in response to a perceived growth in drug use and abuse among residents, especially minors, of Ann Arbor and the surrounding areas, and as a reaction to a believed Ann Arbor drug "malaise." The organization collected data from a wide variety of sources before submitting a final report of recommendations to the Ann Arbor City Council and disbanding in 1990. Throughout its existence, the group, and Martin in particular, also pursued a number of policies to be put in place by the Ann Arbor City Government. Most notable among these, were attempts to amend the city's five-dollar "pot law," in response to feelings that Ann Arbor was too favorable environment for marijuana use.
The documents in this record group detail the creation, development, organization, and work of the Ann Arbor Anti-Substance Abuse Task Force. Also featured are documents, which provide insight into the events leading to the formation of the organization, as well as materials that chronicle the immediate effects of their recommendations. These papers are divided into five series: Correspondence, Committees, Data Collection, Report to City Council, and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Anti-Substance Abuse Task Force.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; Drug abuse--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Substance abuse--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Prevention.; Youth--Drug use--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Martin, Terry.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series consists of both letters and memoranda sent to and from Terry Martin and other task force members. The materials are organized chronologically into six folders with a seventh folder of undated letters beginning the series. In the cases of form letters used by the task force, the original blank letter has been kept with an attached list of recipients, when available.
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1988 (Box 1)
  - January-June, 1989 (Box 1)
  - July-December, 1989 (Box 1)
  - January-June, 1990 (Box 1)
  - July-December, 1990 (Box 1)
  - 1991 (Box 1)
- Committees
  The second series, Committees, is made up of materials from meetings and other documents, which concern related groups that are not the central task force itself. These include: The Ann Arbor City Council Anti-Substance Abuse Policy Committee, focus groups established as a means of data collection by the Task Force, the Task Force subcommittees, and the Task Force Video Ad-Hoc Committee. There are four task force subcommittees: Enforcement, Data Collection, Supply Reduction, and Prevention.
  - Ann Arbor City Council Anti-Substance Abuse Policy Committee (Box 1)
  - Task Force Focus Groups (Box 1)
  - Task Force Subcommittees (Box 1)
    (Enforcement, Data Collection, Supply Reduction and Prevention Subcommittee documents)
  - Task Force Video Ad-Hoc Committee (Box 1)
- Data Collection
  The Data Collection series consists of only two folders. The first is a collection of surveys, which provide an idea of the types of questions and methods used by the task force. The second folder is made up of statistics, survey results, charts, and other documents containing the raw data collected by the organization.
  - Surveys, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Data collection forms (Box 1)
  - Preliminary Analysis of Substance Abuse Survey, February 6, 1990, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Raw Data (Box 1)
- Report to City Council
  The Report to the City Council features an assortment of materials used in, and regarding, the presentation given to the Ann Arbor City Council upon the completion of the task force's findings. Also included is the actual final report, and the community-wide survey supplement.
  - Report Materials (Box 1)
  - Final Report (Box 1)
  - Final Report additions (Box 1)
- Topical Files, 1987-1992
  The Topical File series is a wide variety of items, sorted into alphabetical order, unrelated to the other series of the collection, and expansive enough to warrant their own folder. Of particular interest will be the minutes and agendas of the task force meetings, the file regarding the resignation of several task force members, and materials related to efforts to change the city's marijuana legislation.
  - Ann Arbor City Council Resolutions (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Five Dollar "Pot Law" (Box 1)
  - Domestic Violence Project, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Financial Documents (Box 1)
  - Housing and Urban Development Program (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Membership List (Box 2)
  - Organizational Documents (Box 2)
  - Peace Neighborhood; include study "Substance Abuse Prevention and Treatment Programming Low Income Situations Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 2)
  - Press Releases and Clippings (Box 2)
  - Program and Staff Proposals (Box 2)
  - Short History of Ann Arbor's Marijuana Drug Trade, June 1989 (Box 2)
  - Task Force Member Resignation Incident (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous: Pat Duford working files, 6 folders (Box 2)